<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Flip Side Racing Software</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Jeremy</firstname><surname>Auten</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Flip Side Racing</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>2011/03/04</pubdate>
  </info>

  <chapter xml:id="GettingStarted">
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <section>
      <title>General Information</title>

      <para>Flip Side Racing Software is an open source, cross platform lap
      counting software project that currently supports the <link
      linkend="CoreSpeedway">Core Speedway</link>, <link
      linkend="KyoshoIC">Kyosho IC</link>, <link linkend="I-Lap">I-Lap</link>,
      <link linkend="Trackmate">Trackmate</link>, <link
      linkend="AMBrc">AMBrc</link> and <link
      linkend="Robitronic">Robitronic</link> lap counters or the use of a
      keyboard. This software has been developed with a great amount of useful
      input from the Mini-Z community at the <link
      xlink:href="http://mini-zracer.com/forums/">Mini-ZRacer.com
      Forums</link> and was designed with the <link linkend="HFAYOLPS">How
      Fast Are You OnLine Point Series</link> in mind. If you have not looked
      into the How Fast Are You OnLine Point Series you should take a moment
      to visit their website at <link
      xlink:href="http://www.howfastareyou.com">www.howfastareyou.com</link>.
      Any group that has at least 3 people, <link
      xlink:href="http://www.rcptracks.com">RCP track</link> and a suitable
      lap counter can race against people around the world.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Features</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Supports <link linkend="CoreSpeedway">Core Speedway</link>,
          <link linkend="KyoshoIC">Kyosho IC</link>, <link
          linkend="I-Lap">I-Lap</link>, <link
          linkend="Trackmate">Trackmate</link>, <link
          linkend="AMBrc">AMBrc</link> and <link
          linkend="Robitronic">Robitronic</link> lap counters</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use cheap generic <link linkend="RFID">RFID</link> tags</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link linkend="TTS">Text to speech</link> engine, the software
          will attempt to pronounce names and can dynamically announce things
          during the race such as ranks, individual best laps and time
          remaining</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link linkend="LiveGraphing">Live graphing</link>, during a
          race you can look at the graphs of racers progress</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add racers anytime during a race, useful especially for
          practices</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Start races without adding anyone before the race, useful for
          practices</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Generates <link linkend="HFAYOLPS">How Fast Are You OnLine
          Point Series</link> information</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HTML and XML data race report export</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Available for Windows and Mac</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open source</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting up the Hardware</title>

      <para>The first step is to set up the lap counting hardware. Use the
      following steps to quickly get the hardware set up.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Go to the <link linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General
          Config</link> Screen using the General Config. button on the upper
          right hand of the window.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>On the <link linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General
          Config</link> Screen go down to the <link
          linkend="HardwareSettings">Hardware Settings</link> section on the
          lower left of the window.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the hardware type from the drop down menu. If you are
          using the <link linkend="Keyboard">Keyboard</link> this go to the
          last step, otherwise proceed to the next step.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For the <link linkend="Hardware">hardware</link> lap counters
          you must select the correct <link linkend="COMPort">COM Port</link>
          from the <link linkend="COMDeviceSelection">COM Device
          Selection</link> drop down menu and click Save Connection. The
          connection will save even if you select the wrong <link
          linkend="COMPort">COM Port</link>, if you are unsure of what <link
          linkend="COMPort">COM Port</link> is the correct one refer to the
          <link linkend="COMPort">COM Port hardware documentation</link>. If
          lap counting hardware does not appear to be detected by your
          Operating System you may need to install a driver, further
          information can be found in the <link linkend="DeviceDriver">Device
          Driver</link> section of the <link
          linkend="Hardware">Hardware</link> chapter.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>While you are still on the <link
          linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> Screen enter
          your <link linkend="ClubName">Club Name</link> under the <link
          linkend="ClubInfo">Club Info</link> and select your club logo for
          the <link linkend="ClubLogo">Report Logo Image</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating Racers</title>

      <para>After correctly setting up your hardware you are ready to create
      racers. You must create racers before you start your first race. Use the
      following steps to create some new racers.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Go to the <link linkend="EditRacersScreen">Edit Racers</link>
          Screen using the Edit Racers button on the upper portion of the
          window.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click the <link linkend="CreateNewRacer">Create New
          Racer</link> button to create a new racer with blank
          information.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Now that a new blank racer has been created the information
          about the racer needs to be populated, the only required fields are
          the Name and the UID though it is recommended that you also select
          an image for the racer. How the UID is populated depends on the
          hardware you are using.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Core Speedway:</emphasis> To get the
              UID of a racer with the <link linkend="CoreSpeedway">Core
              Speedway</link> lap counter put a car with an <link
              linkend="RFID">RFID Tag</link> above the lap counter antenna and
              click the scan button.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Other Hardware:</emphasis> To get
              the UID of a racer with other <link
              linkend="Hardware">hardware</link> lap counters click the scan
              button and drive a car with a transponder past the lap
              counter.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Keyboard:</emphasis> If you are
              using the <link linkend="Keyboard">Keyboard</link> to register
              laps put they key that you want to use for the racer in the UID
              field.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>After you have entered all the information in about the racer
          click the Save button to save the racers information. All
          information is stored in the database.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For each additional racer that you need to create you must
          click the <link linkend="CreateNewRacer">Create New Racer</link>
          button first and follow the above steps.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting Up a Race</title>

      <para>Now that you have set up your hardware and created some racers you
      are ready to set up a race. Use the following steps to set up your first
      race.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>All the race settings are defined on the <link
          linkend="RaceConfigScreen">Race Config</link> Screen, go to the
          <link linkend="RaceConfigScreen">Race Config</link> Screen by
          clicking the Race Config. button on the top of the window.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>While it is not required when the <link
          linkend="RaceName">Auto Name</link> feature is enabled you can enter
          a <link linkend="RaceName">Race Name</link>. The <link
          linkend="RaceName">Race Name</link> field is added to each race name
          along with the round type, date and time.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>By default there are no <link linkend="RaceProfiles">Race
          Profiles</link> created, <link linkend="RaceProfiles">Race
          Profiles</link> can be useful but are not required. You can change
          all the race settings manually on this page to what you need for
          your race. If you have a multiple different types of races that you
          run it would be convenient to create a <link
          linkend="RaceProfiles">Race Profile</link> for each race so that you
          can select a profile instead of having to change each setting
          manually.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you have any questions about the available settings for a
          race you can find further information in the <link
          linkend="RaceConfigScreen">Race Config</link> chapter.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>After adjusting any race settings you are ready to run a race,
          proceed to the next section <link linkend="RunningaRace">Running a
          Race</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="RunningaRace">
      <title>Running a Race</title>

      <para>You are now ready to run a race, all races run from the <link
      linkend="RaceScreen">Race Screen</link>. When a race is started the
      software will automatically add racers to the race as they are detected.
      Below are a few details about this feature.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Automatically Add Racers:</emphasis> The
          software has the ability to add any detected car to a race
          automatically. They must have already been defined in the <link
          linkend="EditRacersScreen">Edit Racers</link> Screen which you did
          earlier when creating new racers. The first time the car is detected
          it will be added to the race automatically then the next time they
          cross the lap counter will be counted as their first lap.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To start a race you must click the Start Race button. Clicking
      this button will begin the <link linkend="CountDownTime">Count
      Down</link> to start the race. The race will then run according to the
      <link linkend="RaceType">Race Type</link> you selected on the <link
      linkend="RaceConfigScreen">Race Config</link> Screen.</para>

      <para>During a race many features are disabled, you can only go to the
      <link linkend="RaceScreen">Race</link> or <link
      linkend="StatisticsScreen">Statistics</link> Screens. The <link
      linkend="RaceScreen">Race Screen</link> will show you the current ranks
      and other information about the race while the <link
      linkend="StatisticsScreen">Statistics Screen</link> will show a <link
      linkend="LiveGraphing">Live Graph</link> of the current racers during a
      race.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Viewing Results</title>

      <para>After you have completed a race you can go back and view the
      results for any prior race. To see information about previous races you
      need to go to the <link linkend="StatisticsScreen">Statistics
      Screen</link>. On this screen you have the ability graph previous races,
      individual racers and generate reports about those races.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="GeneralConfigScreen">
    <title>General Config Screen</title>

    <para>The General Config. Screen contains various settings that control
    the overall operation of the program including setting up the hardware,
    defining audio settings, and your general club information. You access the
    General Config. Screen by clicking the General Config. button on the top
    row of buttons in the program. All settings that are changed on this
    screen are saved immediately to the preferences.xml file except for the
    COM Device Selection settings.</para>

    <section xml:id="ClubInfo">
      <title>Club Info</title>

      <para>The settings under the Club Info heading are used throughout the
      program.</para>

      <section xml:id="ClubName">
        <title>Club Name</title>

        <para>Make sure to set your club name correctly. The Club Name is used
        by the various reports generated by the program, such as the Race
        Report, Racer Inventory Report and the <link linkend="HFAYOLPS">HFAY
        OLPS</link> export. By setting this value correctly any time you
        generate a report your club name will be already in the report.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ClubLogo">
        <title>Report Logo Image</title>

        <para>The Report Logo image is used by the two reports generated by
        the program, the <link linkend="GenerateRaceReport">Race Report</link>
        and the <link linkend="GenerateRacerInventoryReport">Racer Inventory
        Report</link>. The image that you set here will be included in any new
        reports that you generate.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="GUISettings">
      <title>GUI Settings</title>

      <para>GUI Settings change how the <link linkend="RaceScreen">Race
      Screen</link> and <link linkend="StatisticsScreen">Statistics
      Screen</link> operate. By using these settings you can allow more racers
      per race or help a machine that may be too slow for live
      graphing.</para>

      <section xml:id="ChangeTextColor">
        <title>Slot Colors</title>

        <para>The Slot Colors list box controls what color the text will be on
        the <link linkend="RaceScreen">Race Screen</link> for each racer slot
        and on the <link linkend="StatisticsScreen">Statistics Screen</link>
        for each graph line. Click on the text in the list box to change the
        color. A window will pop up allowing you to select any color.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="MaximumRacers">
        <title>Maximum Number of Racers</title>

        <para>This sets the maximum number of racers allowed in a race. The
        default setting is 8 but you can go as high as 24 racers in a race. Be
        careful, if you set this value too high you may not be able to see all
        the racers on the screen. Modify the row spacing to increase the
        number of racers that can be seen on the screen at once.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Row Spacing</title>

        <para>Changing the Row Spacing changes the amount of space between
        each racer on the <link linkend="RaceScreen">Race Screen</link>. By
        making this value smaller you can fit more racers on the screen at
        once. The default value is 13. With this default value 8 racers will
        fit on a XGA (1024x720) screen.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="DisableLiveGraphing">
        <title>Disable Live Race Graphing</title>

        <para><link linkend="LiveGraphing">Live Graphing</link> can be a CPU
        intensive operation especially if you have a long race with a large
        number of racers. The Disable Live Race Graphing option allows you to
        permanently disable this feature for computers that may not be fast
        enough. Though as long as you are not on the <link
        linkend="StatisticsScreen">Statistics Screen</link> the live graphing
        will not be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ThemeButton">
        <title>Theme</title>

        <para>On the General Config Screen you can select which theme to apply
        to the program. Themes modify the appearance and sound effects of the
        program. To change settings of a theme click the Manage Theme button
        under the Theme heading. More information about themes can be found in
        the <link linkend="Theme">Theme</link> chapter.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="HardwareSettings">
      <title>Hardware Settings</title>

      <para>The Hardware Settings heading contains options for configuring any
      external devices you are using with the software.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Hardware Type</title>

        <para>You must set the correct Hardware Type for the application to
        operate. If you set this to <link linkend="Keyboard">Keyboard</link>
        then for each racer you must set the <link linkend="UID">UID</link> to
        the key you are going to press to register a lap for them. For the
        other <link linkend="Hardware">hardware types</link> you must define
        the correct COM port for the software to operate.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="Accuracy">
        <title>Accuracy</title>

        <para>Accuracy is set to automatic by default. This setting defines
        what level of accuracy the lap counter provides for lap times. It is
        recommended to keep this on automatic as this will use the appropriate
        accuracy for your defined hardware type but you can manually define
        0.01 second or 0.001 second accuracy if needed.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="COMDeviceSelection">
        <title>COM Device Selection</title>

        <para>If you have a <link linkend="Hardware">hardware</link> lap
        counter you must select the correct COM port here for the software to
        operate. After selecting the correct COM port you must click the Save
        Connection button for the settings to be saved and for communication
        with the lap counter to be initialized. After saving this setting it
        will automatically be used.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="SecondaryCOMDevice">
        <title>Secondary COM Device Selection</title>

        <para>In the event that you have a second lap counter connected to the
        computer you must define what COM port it uses using the Secondary COM
        Device Selection setting. After selecting the correct COM port click
        the Save Connection button to save the settings and initialize
        communication. The secondary lap counter will only be used for
        register laps, it does not work with the <link
        linkend="EditRacersScreen">Edit Racers</link> Screen. Only use this
        setting if you have a second lap counter attached.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Relay Board COM Device Selection</title>

        <para>A <link linkend="RelayBoard">DLPIOR4 Relay Board</link> can be
        used to control Start/Stop lights. The application will control the
        relay board, during the starting race countdown the relay board can
        will have Relay 4 active until 2 seconds left in the countdown, at 2
        seconds it will switch Relay 4 off and Relay 3 on, at 1 second it will
        switch Relay 3 off and Relay 2 on and finally at the start of the race
        it will switch Relay 2 off and Relay 1 on. When the race time limit or
        lap limit is reached race Relay 1 will turn off and Relay 2 will turn
        on. When everyone has finished their final laps or timed out Relay 2
        will turn off and Relay 4 will turn on. You can connect lights to
        these relays to have a start/stop light for races.</para>

        <para>If you have <link linkend="RelayBoard">this relay board</link>
        attached to the computer use this setting to define what COM port it
        is using. After selecting the correct COM port click the Save
        Connection button to save the settings and initialize
        communication.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="GeneralSettings">
      <title>General Settings</title>

      <para>Under the General Settings heading is settings that do not fit in
      other headings.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Audio</title>

        <para>If for some reason you need to disable the audio or are running
        this application on a system that does not have a sound card use this
        setting to turn off the audio. This will disable any <link
        linkend="SoundEffects">sounds</link> and <link
        linkend="TTS">speech</link> of the application.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Check for Updates</title>

        <para>The Check for Updates setting allows the program to see if there
        is a newer version of the program available for download. This check
        will happen each time the program launches. If there is a new version
        available you will be prompted with a pop up window asking if you want
        to go to the website and download it or not. When the software checks
        for an update it will send various information about your setup to the
        server. This information includes the version number, your club name,
        number of racers, number of races, hardware type and operating system.
        Use this setting to disable checking for updates.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="SpeechFile">
        <title>Speech File</title>

        <para>This drop down will automatically populate with the speech files
        available when the program is launched. Speech files are stored in the
        translations directory. By default the americanenglish speech file is
        used. It is possibly to use additional translations such as German and
        French or to create your own translation. To learn more about
        translations read the <link linkend="Translations">Translations</link>
        section in <link linkend="AdvancedTopics">Advanced
        Topics</link>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Close Program Prompt</title>

        <para>This option allows you to control if and when you get prompted
        about whether or not you want to close the program. If this setting is
        set to "Always" then any time you try to close the program you will be
        prompted to confirm your action. If this setting is set to "During
        Races" then you will only be prompted if a race is active, while if
        you set it to "Never" you will not be prompted at any time to confirm
        you want to close the program.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Import All Data</title>

        <para>If you have a new copy of the software and you want to import
        all settings, racers and races from an existing copy use this option.
        When you click this button you will be prompted to select the folder
        where the existing copy is located. The program will then overwrite
        the information in the new copy with the data from the existing
        copy.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Database Utilities</title>

      <para>Many of the functions of the application are using a <link
      linkend="Database">SQLite database</link> to store relational
      information. Under this heading you will find utilities to modify some
      aspects of the <link linkend="Database">database</link>.</para>

      <section xml:id="EditMakeModel">
        <title>Edit Make/Models</title>

        <para>When creating or editing racers you have the ability to select a
        Make and Model of the car they are driving. To add options to the
        <link linkend="EditRacersScreen">Edit Racers</link> screen for Makes
        and Models you need to use the Edit Make/Model utility. By clicking
        this button a small window will pop up allow you to create new Makes
        or add Models for a particular Make of a car. This information is then
        stored back in the <link linkend="Database">database</link>
        permanently.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Import/Export Racers</title>

        <para>The Import/Export Racers buttons allow you to import or export
        the racer information from the <link linkend="EditRacersScreen">Edit
        Racers</link> screen. This does not include any race information, only
        information about that particular racer such as name, <link
        linkend="UID">UID</link> and other car details. Records with a
        duplicate <link linkend="UID">UID</link> will cause an error and not
        be imported.</para>

        <para>This could be useful if you are traveling to another club, you
        can export the racer information from your computer and then send it
        to the other club director who then imports it. Then when your group
        arrives for racing all your cars are already entered into the program.
        Or if you want to start with a clean <link
        linkend="Database">database</link> but do not want to reenter all the
        racer information you can export the racer information download a new
        copy of the software and import your racer information.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="GenerateRacerInventoryReport">
        <title>Racer Inventory Report</title>

        <para>The Racer Inventory Report button generates a report showing all
        the individual racer information. This report includes the club name
        and log at the top followed by a table of racer information. The
        report is automatically saved to a directory under the reports
        directory that is named Racer Inventory followed by the date and time.
        Within the Racer Inventory Report directory will be a HTML report
        along with the original XML data and a copy of the logo.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Vacuum</title>

        <para>If you encounter slow database performance the Vacuum operation
        can help speed things up. Vacuum will remove unused space, defragment
        and compress your database allowing for faster operations. If you
        frequently delete races your database can become very fragmented and
        this operation would be beneficial.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="EmailSettings">
      <title>Email Settings</title>

      <para>Using the settings in this section will allow the software to
      automatically send out race reports to admins and/or racers after a race
      has been completed. For racers to receive email you must define an email
      address for that racer on the <link linkend="EditRacersScreen">Edit
      Racers</link> screen.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Server Name</title>

        <para>This must be set to the SMTP server name for your email
        provider. For example if you are using Gmail this setting must be set
        to smtp.gmail.com</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Server Port</title>

        <para>This is the port number for your SMTP server, it is set to 25 by
        default. If your email provider does not indicate a port number and is
        not using encryption then this is a safe default. If you are using
        encryption then the port number is most likely 587 or 465. For example
        in the case of Gmail they are using encryption and have the port
        number set to 587. Your email provider should indicate what port
        number to use.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>From Address</title>

        <para>You must set this field to your email address. This is the
        address that the email's will appear to come from. If you do not set
        it to the address for your account your email provider may reject the
        email as spam.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Admin Addresses</title>

        <para>Enter a comma separated list of email addresses into this field.
        If you define the recipients to include admins the listed admin email
        addresses will get a copy of each race report sent whether they are in
        the race or not.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Username</title>

        <para>Set this setting to the username of your email account.
        Depending on your email provider this may be a normal username or it
        may be your from email address. For example in the case of Gmail this
        is your from email address.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Password</title>

        <para>Set this to the password for your email account. To protect your
        password it is not displayed on the screen, only dots will
        appear.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Recipients</title>

        <para>Recipients defines who will receive race reports. This can be
        set to Admins, Racers or Admins and Racers. If set to include Racers
        you must set the email addresses for each racer that wants to receive
        the reports. You do this by editing the racers information on the
        <link linkend="EditRacersScreen">Edit Racers</link> screen.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Race Reports</title>

        <para>This setting defines which type or races will send a report. By
        default the software will only send out reports for Mains. You can
        change this to send out reports for all races, or to send out reports
        for all races but practices. Race reports are sent immediately after
        the race is completed.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>SSL Encryption</title>

        <para>Enable SSL Encryption if your email provider allows this option.
        If your email server supports this make sure to set the server port to
        the correct number. For example Gmail requires the use of port 587
        with SSL Encryption.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Test Button</title>

        <para>After you have defined the necessary email settings you can test
        the email functionality using the test button. This will send a basic
        email message to the defined from address. If you do not receive this
        test message then either check your junk mail folder or verify your
        email settings.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="EditRacersScreen">
    <title>Edit Racers Screen</title>

    <para>The Edit Racers Screen is used for creating, editing, deleting and
    viewing racer information. All racer information is stored in the <link
    linkend="Database">database</link>.</para>

    <section xml:id="CreateNewRacer">
      <title>Creating Racers</title>

      <para>To create a new racer you must first click the Create New Racer
      button. Clicking this button creates a new blank record for a racer that
      you can then edit and save. Each new racer must have a <link
      linkend="UID">UID</link> and a name defined. All the other fields are
      optional though selecting a <link linkend="RacerImages">Racer
      Image</link> is recommended. After you have entered the info in for a
      racer you must click the Save button to save the record. The racer will
      then show up in the racer table on the right of the screen.</para>

      <para>If you wish to copy a UID for an existing racer you can click the
      drop down arrow on the left of the UID field to select a particular UID
      from the list of available ones. While multiple racers can have the same
      UID only 1 racer with a particular UID may be enabled at a time.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Core Speedway Specific Info</title>

        <para>When creating a new racer for the <link
        linkend="CoreSpeedway">Core Speedway</link> lap counter after you
        click the Create New Racer button you must click the Scan button next
        to the <link linkend="UID">UID</link> field. The car you are scanning
        must be on top of the antenna loop. The scan button will perform one
        quick scan, if a tag is detected the <link linkend="UID">UID</link>
        will display in the <link linkend="UID">UID</link> field.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Other Lap Counter Hardware Info</title>

        <para>When creating a new racer for other <link
        linkend="Hardware">hardware</link> based lap counters after you click
        the Create New Racer button you must click the Scan button next to the
        <link linkend="UID">UID</link> field. The scan will run for 5 seconds,
        during this time the car you are scanning must then be driven over the
        antenna ribbon or below the detection bridge. If a new car is detected
        the <link linkend="UID">UID</link> will display in the <link
        linkend="UID">UID</link> field.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Keyboard Specific Info</title>

        <para>The software has the ability to use the <link
        linkend="Keyboard">keyboard</link> for registering the laps instead of
        using lap counter hardware. If you want to use this mode of operation
        each racer must have the <link linkend="UID">UID</link> field set to
        unique key. You are not limited to just numbers, it can be almost any
        key on the keyboard. Do not use the "r" key though, this key is used
        to announce the ranks during a race.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Editing Racers</title>

      <para>To edit an existing racer you must click on the racer in the table
      on the race side of the screen. After click the racer all the
      information about the racer will be displayed in the fields on the left
      side of the screen. After you have made changes to the record you must
      click Save to save the changes.</para>

      <para>If you need to change the <link linkend="UID">UID</link> of a
      racer then first select the racer that needs changed and then if you are
      using <link linkend="Hardware">lap counting hardware</link> you use the
      Scan button the same way as when you create racers. As long as the <link
      linkend="UID">UID</link> is not already used by another racer the scan
      will overwrite the existing <link linkend="UID">UID</link> and then you
      can save the racers information. If you are using the <link
      linkend="Keyboard">keyboard</link> for lap counting then you can just
      manually update the <link linkend="UID">UID</link> field.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="RacerImages">
      <title>Racer Image</title>

      <para>When creating a racer you can select a racer image. The software
      comes with an assortment of images but you can also use your own. At
      most the application will display 100x40 pixels of the image you select,
      the image is automatically resized down to 100x40 pixels.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Speak Field</title>

      <para>The Speak field under the name allows you to have the program say
      a name other than what is in the Name field. This is useful in cases
      where someone may have their name match an online ID such as pinwc4 but
      the persons name is actually Jeremy. You can put pinwc4 as the Name and
      put Jeremy in the Speak field. The program will announce the name Jeremy
      but any reports will show the name pinwc4.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Email Field</title>

      <para>This field defines the email address for this specific racer. You
      must set email addresses for each racer that wants to automatically
      receive a race report. Additionally you will need to have the correct
      email settings defined in the <link linkend="EmailSettings">Email
      Settings</link> section of the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> screen.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Enabled</title>

      <para>The enabled checkbox is used to allow you to share cars or
      transponders with other racers. While you can define multiple racers
      with the same UID only one racer with a shared <link
      linkend="UID">UID</link> may be enabled at a time. To enable a different
      racer that is sharing a transponder you may either click the enabled
      checkbox in the table showing all the racers which will then
      automatically save the change or you can select the individual racer in
      the table and then edit that racers information and click save manually.
      When you enable a racer the software will automatically disable any
      other racer that shares that <link linkend="UID">UID</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Race Car Specific Information</title>

      <para>Details about how to change the options available under the Race
      Car Specific Information heading can be found in the <link
      linkend="AdvancedTopics">Advanced Topics</link> chapter under the <link
      linkend="RaceCarInfoPopUp">Adding Options to the Edit Racer
      Screen</link> section.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Deleting Racers</title>

      <para>Deleting a racer is simple. Just select the racer in the table on
      the right side of the screen and then click Delete.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">WARNING: This operation is permanent, there
      is no undo.</emphasis></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="RaceConfigScreen">
    <title>Race Config Screen</title>

    <para>On the Race Config. Screen you define all the settings for a race,
    including the race type, name, time limits, etc. Each time the application
    is launched it will default to the last settings or race profile
    selected.</para>

    <section xml:id="RaceName">
      <title>Race Name</title>

      <para>Each race that is ran must have a unique name. By default auto
      naming of races is enabled. This feature will add the date, time, and
      round type to whatever is filled in to the Race Name field. Even if you
      do not enter any information into the race name field the race name will
      still be unique. If you disable the Auto Name feature you must enter in
      a unique name for each race before the race is started.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="RaceProfiles">
      <title>Race Profiles</title>

      <para>Race profiles are a collection of the race settings other than the
      Race Name settings that are permanently saved to the <link
      linkend="Database">database</link>. This allows you to easily retrieve
      common settings for different race types used by your club. Race
      profiles are not required to be created but they are usual for switching
      between race types such as practice races versus mains, or endurance
      races versus lap races.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Create Race Profile</title>

        <para>To create a new race profile just click the Create button under
        the Race Profiles heading. This will pop up a small window where you
        must enter a unique race profile name. When you click OK on the pop up
        window the program will create a new race profile using the settings
        that were defined under the Race Profiles section of the
        screen.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Delete Race Profile</title>

        <para>Deleting a race profile is simple, just select the Race Profile
        in the pop up menu and click the Delete button.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">WARNING: This operation is permanent,
        there is no undo.</emphasis></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Save Race Profile</title>

        <para>After changing settings for a Race Profile you just click the
        Save button for them to be saved for later use. If you do not click
        the save button the settings will be used for those races but after
        the application is closed and opened again the unsaved settings will
        be lost.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Race Settings</title>

      <para>Below the Race Profiles section the individual race settings are
      listed. If race profiles are not being used these settings will default
      to the last settings used when the application was closed. If a race
      profile is not used the settings are stored in preferences.xml file
      otherwise they are stored in the <link
      linkend="Database">database</link>.</para>

      <section xml:id="RaceType">
        <title>Race Type</title>

        <para>The Race Type selected changes how the race is tracked, by time
        or by number of laps. There are 4 race types currently
        supported.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Timed Race</title>

          <para>For a timed race the race will end after the time limit has
          been reached. When the time limit is reached all racers must
          complete their final lap before the time out. When all racers have
          completed their final lap or timed out the race will end.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Lap Race</title>

          <para>In a lap race the race will end after the first person reaches
          the lap limit. After the lap limit has been reached all other racer
          must complete their final lap before the time out. When all racers
          have completed their final lap or timed out the race will
          end.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Lap and Timed Race</title>

          <para>With a lap and timed race the race will end after either the
          lap limit or the time limit is reached. When either the lap or time
          limit has been reached all remaining racers must complete their
          final lap before the time out. When all racers have completed their
          final lap or timed out the race will end.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Staggered Time Race</title>

          <para>A staggered race is similar to a timed race except each racer
          gets their own clock based on the time limit setting. Each
          individual racers clock will not start until after the first time
          they cross the lap counter. The race will end after the final racers
          time limit is reached and they have completed their final lap or
          timed out.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Free Play Race</title>

          <para>A Free Play race type is intended for open track time. It is
          not really a true race type, no results are stored. It has the
          following characteristics:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The race does not end automatically, no lap limit or time
              limit. You must manually end it by pressing the <link
              linkend="EndRaceButton">End Race Button</link> on the <link
              linkend="RaceScreen">Race Screen</link>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Results are not stored to the database after the session
              is ended.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Racers are removed from the race screen if they have not
              gotten a lap within the <link linkend="TimeOut">Time Out</link>
              value on the Race Config Screen.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Racers can join the session at any time, the first time
              they cross the lap counter is considered their start time for
              calculating lap times.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Racers can rejoin a session after they have been timed
              out, all information has been reset for them including lap
              counts, times and best lap.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>No rank or time announcements will be made.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Overall and personal best lap times will be
              announced.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>On the <link linkend="RaceScreen">Race Screen</link> the
              pace column will show the average lap time.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Ranking on <link linkend="RaceScreen">Race Screen</link>
              is configurable.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Racers can be manually deleted during the race by double
              clicking on their name or picture.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Number of Laps</title>

        <para>This setting defines the lap limit for a Lap or Lap and Time
        based races. You can type values into the field or use the +/- buttons
        to increment and decrement the value by 1 lap.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Time Limit</title>

        <para>For Timed, Lap and Timed and Staggered Time based races the Time
        Limit value defines how long the race will run. The value in this
        field is based on minutes. You can type values into the field or use
        the +/- buttons to increment and decrement the value by 1
        minute.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Minimum Lap Time</title>

        <para>The Minimum Lap Time defines the quickest lap time that will be
        accepted by the software. If a lap is less than this value it will not
        be recorded. You can enter a value into the field or use the +/-
        buttons to increment and decrement the value by 1 second.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Round Type</title>

        <para>The Round Type drop down defines whether this race is a
        Practice, Heat, Qualifier or Main. This information is used for the
        summary of the race, the race auto naming field and will show up in
        the race report.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="CountDownTime">
        <title>Starting Count Down</title>

        <para>When a race is started the count down timer will begin. The
        Count Down Time defines how long the count down before a race will be.
        If audio is enabled the software will start to announce count down
        seconds remaining at 5 seconds. If the Count Down Time is set to 8
        seconds or longer the software will announce "Prepare to Race" and
        then count down.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Ending Count Down</title>

        <para>At the specified number of seconds the program will count down
        the time remaining. For example if set to 5 seconds when only 5
        seconds are left the program will count down 5, 4, 3, 2, 1 and the
        race will end. If this is set to 0 it will not count down.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="TimeOut">
        <title>Time Out</title>

        <para>When the race time or lap limits have been reached the time out
        value will be used to end the race for racers that have not completed
        their final lap. If it takes the racer longer than the time out value
        to finish the final lap their race will be ended.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Count Down Type</title>

        <para>Select the style of count down to use for the races. A
        traditional count down will display the count down time on the screen
        and when the count down reaches 5 seconds it will start saying the
        seconds remaining in the count down. When the countdown reaches 0 the
        starting horn sound will play and the race starts. In an F1 style
        count down instead of displaying the seconds in the count down the
        program will beep the specified number of times set as the starting
        count down number. When it reaches the final beep the program will set
        a random delay between 1 and 10 seconds before playing the starting
        horn and starting the race.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Ending Horn</title>

        <para>This setting defines whether or not the ending horn sound effect
        plays when a race is complete. The sound effect will be triggered in a
        timed race when the time limit is reached. In a lap race it will be
        triggered when the first person reaches the lap limit.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Lap Indication</title>

        <para>By default when a lap is detected the software will beep but
        there are other interesting options available.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Beep</title>

          <para>The default lap indication setting is the beep, this will play
          a beep sounding wav file.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Lap Time</title>

          <para>The Lap Indication can be changed to announce the Lap Time
          using this setting. Each time a new lap is detected the software
          will say the time. For example is a racer just got a lap time of 7.8
          seconds then the software will announce 7.8 seconds.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Lap Difference</title>

          <para>The Lap Different Lap Indication will announce the different
          between a racers best lap time and their current lap time. If it is
          a new best lap for that racer the software will announce the new
          best lap, otherwise it will just be the difference in time between
          their current time and their best lap time. For example if a racer
          has a best lap of 7.6 seconds and they just got a new lap of 7.8
          seconds the software will announce .2 seconds.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Lap Time 1 Decimal, Lap Time 2 Decimals, Lap Difference 1
          Decimal and Lap Difference 2 Decimals</title>

          <para>These options are variations of the Lap Time and Lap
          Difference options that will round the announced time to the
          specified decimal place. For example if you select Lap Time 1
          Decimal and get a lap time of 7.123 the software will announce the
          lap time as 7.1.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Enable Rank Announcements</title>

        <para>If the Enable Rank Announcements setting is enabled then
        periodically during a race the current ranks of each racer will be
        announced. Set the Rank Announcement Interval to define when the
        announcements occur. You can also hit the "r" key at any time and the
        software will announce the current ranks.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Rank Announcement Interval</title>

        <para>The Rank Announcement Interval defines how often the current
        ranks of each racer will be announced if the Enable Rank Announcements
        feature is enabled. This value sets the number of minutes between rank
        announcements. You can also hit the "r" key at any time and the
        software will announce the current ranks.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Rank Method</title>

        <para>The Rank Method option allows you to change how racers are
        ranked during a race.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Total Laps</title>

          <para>This ranking method ranks by the total laps followed by the
          time they were completed in.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Best Lap</title>

          <para>This ranking method ranks by the best lap times. This is
          useful for qualifying rounds.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Average Lap</title>

          <para>This ranking method ranks by the average lap time. This method
          of ranking is useful for the free play race mode or staggered start
          races.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Rank Change Speech</title>

        <para>This setting configures the speech settings for announcing rank
        changes during a race. If it is set to Lead Change then the program
        will only announce when someone takes the lead. If it is set to Any
        Change then the program will announce a rank change any time someone
        moves up in rank.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Best Lap Speech</title>

        <para>This option allows you to change when best laps are announced.
        You can choose between none, personal or overall. When set to personal
        each races individual best lap time will be announced when it occurs
        during the race. If set to overall individual racers best lap times
        will not be announced, only the best lap overall will be announced
        during the race.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Start Race Button</title>

      <para>The Start Race button will take you to the <link
      linkend="RaceScreen">Race Screen</link> and automatically start the
      race.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="RaceScreen">
    <title>Race Screen</title>

    <para>The Race Screen is the main screen used for starting and running a
    race. When a race is running this is the screen that shows you the current
    rank and information about each driver along with the timer for the race.
    There is also a count down light graphic towards the top right of the
    screen that changes during the count down before the race.</para>

    <section xml:id="RaceScreenStartButton">
      <title>Start Race</title>

      <para>To start a race you can click the Start Race button on this
      screen. When the Start Race button is clicked all racers in slots will
      be removed and a count down will occur as defined by the <link
      linkend="CountDownTime">Count Down Time</link> setting on the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> Screen. Racers will
      be added automatically to the race if detected after the count
      down.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Race Information</title>

      <para>While a race is running the information for each racer in a race
      will be updated on this screen each time a new lap is detected. The
      information on this screen currently includes the overall timer along
      with the rank, <link linkend="RacerImages">image</link>, <link
      linkend="EditRacersScreen">name</link>, laps, time of the last lap, last
      lap time, pace and best lap of each racer.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Live Statistics</title>

      <para>Clicking the Live Statistics button will take you to the <link
      linkend="StatisticsScreen">Statistics Screen</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="EndRaceButton">
      <title>End Race</title>

      <para>In the event that you need to end the race early you can click the
      End Race button to end the race immediately. When clicked the race ends
      right then, racers will not be allowed any more laps.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="StatisticsScreen">
    <title>Statistics Screen</title>

    <para>The Statistics Screen can either show you graphs and tables of
    information from previous races or show graphs of the currently running
    race if <link linkend="DisableLiveGraphing">live graphing</link> is
    enabled. If a race is currently running you will only be able to change
    graph types, other functions on this page will not be available.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Graph Types</title>

      <para>Use the Graph Type pop up menu to select what type of graph you
      want to see.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Laps Versus Time</title>

        <para>In the Laps Versus Time graph type the X axis of the graph will
        represent time and the Y axis will represent the total number of
        laps.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Laps Versus Lag</title>

        <para>In the Laps Versus Lag graph the X axis will represent the lap
        number and the Y axis will represent how far behind the leader you are
        for that particular lap.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Time Per Lap</title>

        <para>In the Time Per Lap graph the X axis represents the lap number
        while the Y axis represents lap time.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Rank Versus Time</title>

        <para>In the Rank Versus Time graph the X axis represents time while
        the Y axis represents the rank of the racer.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selecting Races</title>

      <para>If a race is not currently running you can select previous races
      to see the results. To do this just click the race name of interest in
      the top left table on the Statistics Screen. After clicking a record in
      this table the summary table on the right will update with the
      information for each racer and the graph will plot the graph type
      selected.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selecting Racers</title>

      <para>To limit the graphed information to a specific racer and see the
      individual lap information for a racer you must select their name in the
      summary table on the upper right side of the Statistics Screen. This can
      only be done if a race is not currently running. When a racer is
      selected the graph will update with only that racers information and the
      table on the lower left side of the screen will show the individual lap
      information for that racer.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Exporting How Fast Are You OnLine Point Series Data</title>

      <para>The Export HFAY OLPS format button will create a Comma Separated
      Value file containing information needed for each racer for the <link
      linkend="HFAYOLPS">How Fast Are You OnLine Point Series</link>. Select a
      race in from the upper left table and then click the button. A window
      will pop up a window asking you to save the file to a location. The file
      will already be named based on the race name that you have selected. You
      can then send this file to the director of the <link
      linkend="HFAYOLPS">How Fast Are You OnLine Point Series</link> for your
      results to be included with the latest event.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE:</emphasis> The How Fast Are You OnLine
      Point Series requires that the chassis and motor types be defined for
      each racer. Please make sure you have entered this information in for
      each racer participating in the HFAY OLPS before exporting the HFAY OLPS
      data.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="GenerateRaceReport">
      <title>Generate Report</title>

      <para>The Generate Report button will generate a report of the race you
      have selected in the upper left table. This report will include some
      <link linkend="RaceConfigScreen">race configuration</link> information,
      your <link linkend="ClubName">club name</link>, <link
      linkend="ClubLogo">club logo</link>, date and time of the race, summary
      of the race results and individual lap times. The results will be saved
      in a directory named after the <link linkend="RaceName">race name</link>
      under the reports directory. Within this directory will be a web report,
      raw XML data and a copy of the logo. After the report is generated by
      clicking the button the report will then be displayed using your web
      browser. To learn about customizing the appearance of the race report go
      to the <link linkend="CustomizeRaceReport">Customize Race Report</link>
      section.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="EmailReport">
      <title>Email Report</title>

      <para>The Email Report option allows you to manually send an email that
      contains the results for the selected race. This manual generation of
      the email will follow the rules and use the <link
      linkend="EmailSettings">Email Settings</link> defined on the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> screen. For example
      if you have your email settings defined to send an email automatically
      to Admins Only then even if you click this button to manually send race
      results it will still only go to Admins.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Delete Race</title>

      <para>Deleting a race is quite simple. You need to first select the race
      you wish to delete in the table on the upper left side of the Statistics
      Screen and then click the Delete Race button. The application will
      prompt you asking whether or not you are sure you wish to delete the
      race, click yes to permanently delete the race or cancel not to.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Delete Racer Results</title>

      <para>To delete an individual racers results from a race you must first
      select the race in the table on the upper left side of the Statistics
      Screen. After the race is selected you then can select the racer in the
      summary table on the upper right of the screen and click Delete Racer
      Results. Clicking this button will cause a pop up message asking if you
      are really sure you want to delete the racers results. Clicking yes will
      delete the results or cancel will do nothing.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Merge Laps</title>

      <para>In the event that a racer accidentally got counted for 2 laps when
      they should have gotten one you can merge the laps together after the
      race has ended. To merge laps first select the race in the upper left
      table on the Statistics Screen, then select the racer in the summary
      table on the upper right of the screen. This will cause the laps table
      on the lower left of the screen to populate with individual lap
      information. By default the Merge Laps button will merge the time of the
      lap selected in this table with the time of the lap after it unless you
      select the last lap. If the last lap is selected it will merge the time
      with the lap before it.</para>

      <para>Selecting a lap in the lower left hand table and clicking the
      Merge Laps button will cause a pop up asking you if you are sure you
      want to merge laps. Click yes to merge the laps. If yes is clicked the
      laps are merged and the summary information for the race is
      recalculated. This is needed just in case the ranking or other
      statistics of the race change as a result of the lap merger.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Split Lap</title>

      <para>If the lap counter accidentally missed a lap for a race you will
      need to split a lap into 2 laps so that the racer gets proper credit. To
      split a lap for a racer after the race has been ran you must select the
      race in the table on the upper left side of the Statistics Screen and
      then select the racer in the summary table on the upper right side of
      the screen. This will populate individual lap information in the lower
      left table of the screen.</para>

      <para>Select a lap in the lower left hand table and clicking the Slip
      Lap button will cause a pop up asking you if you are sure you want to
      split the lap. Click yes to split the lap. If yes is clicked the lap is
      split and the summary information for the race is recalculated. This is
      needed just in case the ranking or other statistics of the race change
      as a result of the lap split.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="LiveGraphing">
      <title>Live Graphing</title>

      <para>The Statistics Screen is capable of graphing the information of
      the currently running race. As long as the <link
      linkend="DisableLiveGraphing">Live Graphing</link> feature is not
      disabled the statistics screen will show a live graph of the currently
      running race. During live graphing most of the features of the
      Statistics Screen are disabled except for the Graph Type selection. Once
      the race has completed then all the features of this screen are
      available again. Live Graphing can cause older machines to perform too
      slow to properly detect laps so be careful especially if you are running
      really long races.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="HFAYOLPS">
    <title>How Fast Are You OnLine Point Series</title>

    <para>The How Fast Are You OnLine Point Series is a worldwide point series
    that any group can participate in. To compete you need at least 3 people
    racing, 2 Wide L's of <link xlink:href="http://www.rcptracks.com">RCP
    track</link> and a suitable lap counter. The results of your race will be
    combined and ranked with all the other participating clubs around the
    world.</para>

    <para>Each month you group must run a event which comprises of 2 races on
    a specific track design, one clockwise and one counter clockwise. Since
    everyone is running the same layout each month we can then combine the
    race results of each club together to rank everyone for each race and
    season. Each season consists of 5 events, each event consists of 2 races
    and there are 2 seasons a year. You must submit your groups previous race
    results by the first day of each month. At the end of a season your worst
    2 races are dropped from your results and you will get your final
    worldwide ranking for that season.</para>

    <para>Various prizes and awards are available for the top 3 racers, the
    top under 16 years old racers and clubs. The events are quick and easy to
    run but the competition for the top ranking is fierce.</para>

    <para>We hope you will participate with our clubs in this unique and fun
    point series.</para>

    <para>For more information and to register for the series visit the How
    Fast Are You OnLine Point Series site at <link
    xlink:href="http://www.howfastareyou.com">www.howfastareyou.com</link>.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="Hardware">
    <title>Hardware</title>

    <para>The software has support for various types of hardware. This chapter
    details some of the unique things about the supported hardware.</para>

    <section xml:id="COMPort">
      <title>COM Ports</title>

      <para>To communicate with the various hardware that this software
      supports COM ports are used. Even though each of the devices plug in via
      USB the old style COM communication is what is being used. Each of the
      devices have a chip in them to convert from USB to COM. COM ports appear
      differently on each Operating System, here are some specific details for
      each OS.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Windows:</emphasis> In Windows the lap
          counting hardware will probably be the last device in the COM port
          list. If that does not work or you want to know for sure what COM
          port is the correct one you can look in the device manager. To get
          to the Windows device manager go to your Control Panel then to
          Administrative Tools and then Computer Management. Within the window
          that pops up you can look at the device manager. Look under the
          Ports for a USB port created by the <link
          linkend="DeviceDriver">FTDI Driver</link>. This will be the COM port
          you need to use.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Mac OS X:</emphasis> In Mac the device
          will appear in the list as usb- followed by some numbers. If you
          have multiple of these devices you figure out which one is correct
          through the System Profiler. To get to the System Profiler click the
          Apple logo in the top left of your screen and then select About This
          Mac. In the window that pops up click the More Info... button, this
          will launch the System Profiler. In the System Profiler you can
          click USB under Contents to see the various USB devices connected.
          Look for a device using the <link linkend="DeviceDriver">FTDI
          Driver</link>. If no device is found you may need to install the
          <link linkend="DeviceDriver">driver</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Linux:</emphasis> In Linux the device
          will most likely be ttyUSB followed by a number. You may have to
          make a symbolic link to an existing device node such as /dev/ttyS3.
          How to determine the correct COM port can vary per
          distribution.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="DeviceDriver">
      <title>Device Drivers</title>

      <para>All the currently supported lap counting hardware uses the same
      FTDI Driver for communication. If your computer is not recognizing the
      hardware you plugged in you may need to install a driver. You can
      download the latest version of the driver for Windows, Mac and Linux
      from FTDI's website here, <link
      xlink:href="http://www.ftdichip.com/Drivers/VCP.htm">www.ftdichip.com/Drivers/VCP.htm</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="CoreSpeedway">
      <title>Core Speedway</title>

      <para>The Core Speedway lap counter is an <link
      linkend="RFID">RFID</link> reader based on the TI S6350 module or the
      Infinity 166 module. This reader uses 13.56MHz ISO15693 <link
      linkend="RFID">RFID</link> tags for tracking RC cars. Details about the
      TI S6350 hardware can be found at TI's site here, <link
      xlink:href="http://www.ti.com/rfid/shtml/prod-readers-RI-STU-TRDC.shtml">www.ti.com/rfid/shtml/prod-readers-RI-STU-TRDC.shtml</link>.
      The software uses the <link linkend="UID">UID</link> of each <link
      linkend="RFID">RFID</link> tag to uniquely identify each car.</para>

      <para>The Infinity 166 variety of the Core hardware has been sold
      oversees most likely because the existing TI S6350 module was not RoHS
      compliant. The software automatically detects this hardware type and
      changes the timing for this module. While the TI S6350 based RFID reader
      can read 100 times a second the Infinity 166 module is slightly slower
      and can only be polled about 50 times a second.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="KyoshoIC">
      <title>Kyosho IC</title>

      <para>The Kyosho IC lap counter is based on the Melexis 90121 <link
      linkend="RFID">RFID</link> transceiver chip interfaced with an Atmel
      micro controller. The dNaNo and Kyosho tags utilize the 13.56MHz
      ISO15693 <link linkend="RFID">RFID</link> standard for communication.
      The software uses a unique block of data stored on the RFID as the <link
      linkend="UID">UID</link> to identify each car.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="I-Lap">
      <title>I-Lap</title>

      <para>The I-Lap Lap Counter is an IR based lap counting system. Each
      transponder has a 7 character UID that the software will use. When the
      I-Lap hardware is used the software will receive the lap times from the
      lap counter instead of using the internal software timer. When the <link
      linkend="Accuracy">accuracy setting</link> on the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> screen is set to
      automatic the software will use 0.001 second resolution lap times as
      provided by the lap counter.</para>

      <para>As a result of using the hardware lap timer the race pause
      functionality is disabled. This functionality depends on the software
      timer but when using I-Lap hardware we utilize the hardware timer so we
      can have 0.001 second resolution lap times. As a result pausing is not
      supported with this hardware.</para>

      <para>For more information on the I-Lap hardware visit the RC Lap
      Counter website at <link
      xlink:href="???">http://www.rclapcounter.com/</link></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="Robitronic">
      <title>Robitronic</title>

      <para>The Robitronic Lap Counter is an IR based lap counting system.
      Each transponder has a 2 byte <link linkend="UID">UID</link> that the
      software will use. When using the Robitronic Lap Counter the software
      will use the lap times sent by the lap counter instead of the internal
      software timer. The Robitronic hardware has a delay when sending
      detected racer information so you will notice a delay in the software
      for the detection beep and announcements compared to when you cross
      under the bridge.</para>

      <para>Since the Robitronic Lap Counter sends lap timing information
      accurate to 0.001 seconds the automatic <link
      linkend="Accuracy">accuracy setting</link> defined on the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> screen will use
      0.001 second resolution if the hardware type is set to
      Robitronic.</para>

      <para>The ability to pause a race is disabled when using the Robitronic
      Lap Counter. The pause functionality is dependent on the software lap
      timer but when utilizing Robitronic hardware we use the hardware time
      provided by the lap counter to get the 0.001 second resolution. As a
      result pausing is not supported.</para>

      <para>For more information on the Robitronic Lap Counter hardware visit
      the Robitronic web site at <link
      xlink:href="http://www.robitronic.com/">http://www.robitronic.com/</link></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="GKA9805">
      <title>GKA9805</title>

      <para>The GKA9805 is a UHF RFID reader from Global KeyAccess. This
      reader uses EPC G2 tags and is therefore not compatible with the tags
      used for Core or Kyosho RFID lap counters. For more information on this
      reader visit the website at <link
      xlink:href="http://www.globalkeyaccess.com/ProductInfo10000713.aspx">http://www.globalkeyaccess.com/ProductInfo10000713.aspx</link></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="Trackmate">
      <title>Trackmate</title>

      <para>The Trackmate Lap Counter is an IR base lap counting system. Each
      transponder has a 7 character UID that the software will use. When the
      Trackmate hardware is used the software will receive the lap times from
      the lap counter instead of the internal software timer. When the <link
      linkend="Accuracy">accuracy setting</link> on the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> screen is set to
      automatic the software will use 0.001 second resolution lap times as
      provided by the lap counter.</para>

      <para>As a result of using the hardware lap timer the race pause
      functionality is disabled. This functionality depends on the software
      timer but when using I-Lap hardware we utilize the hardware timer so we
      can have 0.001 second resolution lap times. As a result pausing is not
      supported with this hardware.</para>

      <para>For more information on the Trackmate hardware visit the website
      at <link
      xlink:href="http://www.trackmate.com/">http://www.trackmateracing.com/</link></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="AMBrc">
      <title>AMBrc</title>

      <para>Some AMBrc based systems will be able to be used by this lap
      counting software. In order to use an AMBrc based system it must attach
      to the computer through either a serial port or a USB port. When AMBrc
      is selected as a hardware type the software will receive the lap times
      from the lap counter instead of the internal software timer. When the
      <link linkend="Accuracy">accuracy setting</link> on the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> screen is set to
      automatic the software will use 0.001 second resolution lap times as
      provided by the lap counter.</para>

      <para>As a result of using the hardware lap timer the race pause
      functionality is disabled. This functionality depends on the software
      timer but when using I-Lap hardware we utilize the hardware timer so we
      can have 0.001 second resolution lap times. As a result pausing is not
      supported with this hardware.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="WanhaRacing">
      <title>WanhaRacing</title>

      <para>The WanhaRacing lap counter is a custom lap counter based on the
      TRF7960 reader from TI. This hardware is currently under development by
      another group and support is experimental.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="UID">
      <title>UID</title>

      <para>UID stands for Unique IDentifier. Each racer must have a UID. This
      is achieved in various ways depending on the hardware.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Keyboard:</emphasis> For the <link
          linkend="Keyboard">Keyboard</link> when <link
          linkend="CreateNewRacer">Creating a New Racer</link> you must assign
          a unique key to each racer, for example 1 or j. Any key can be used
          except for r,s,e and p which are reserved for <link
          linkend="KeyboardShortcuts">Keyboard Shortcuts</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Core Speedway:</emphasis> For the <link
          linkend="CoreSpeedway">Core Speedway</link> hardware the UID is
          based on the UID of the RFID in the car. When <link
          linkend="CreateNewRacer">Creating a New Racer</link> the scan button
          will pick up the <link linkend="RFID">RFID's</link> UID.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Kyosho IC:</emphasis> With the Kyosho IC
          lap counter the UID of the <link linkend="RFID">RFID</link> is not
          used. Instead each <link linkend="RFID">RFID</link> must have a
          unique block of data on block 1 of the memory on the <link
          linkend="RFID">RFID</link>. Kyosho tags and dNaNo's already have a
          unique block of data but generic tags will not. Generic <link
          linkend="RFID">RFID</link> tags will have to be initialized to work
          with the Kyosho IC lap counter. Refer to the <link
          linkend="KyoshoGenericTags">Using Generic Tags with the Kyosho IC
          Lap Counter</link> section of the <link
          linkend="AdvancedTopics">Advanced Topics</link> chapter for further
          information.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">I-Lap:</emphasis> The I-Lap transponders
          provide a 7 character transponder id that the software detects and
          will use as the UID.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Robitronic:</emphasis> The Robitronic
          transponders use a 2 byte transponder id that the software detects
          and uses as the UID. With only 2 bytes used it is possible there
          will be duplicate id's as there can only be a maximum of 65536 id's
          created. So will possible it is fairly unlikely you will encounter a
          duplicate transponder id.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="RFID">
      <title>RFID Tags</title>

      <para>RFID tags are a small integrated circuit with a larger antenna
      loop for picking up the signal from the RFID reader (lap counter). The
      13.56MHz ISO15693 RFID tags used by this software are a passive tag,
      meaning they do not need a power supply to operate, they pick up their
      power from the RF field generated by the lap counter. Each tag has a
      <link linkend="UID">UID</link> along with a small amount of memory that
      can be used for storing data.</para>

      <para>This software enables the use of generic TI RFID tags with the lap
      counting hardware. For the Core Speedway lap counter nothing more needs
      to be done to use generic tags. With the Kyosho IC lap counter refer to
      the <link linkend="KyoshoGenericTags">Using Generic Tags with the Kyosho
      IC Lap Counter</link> section of the <link
      linkend="AdvancedTopics">Advanced Topics</link> chapter for further
      information.</para>

      <para>Information about recommended generic RFID tags to use with the
      software can be found on the Flip Side Racing website here, <link
      xlink:href="http://www.flipsideracing.org">www.flipsideracing.org</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="RelayBoard">
      <title>Relay Board</title>

      <para>The software has the ability to use DLP Designs DLP-IOR4 USB relay
      board for controlling a stop/start light tree. This board is capable of
      handling up to 60W light bulbs. The relay board itself does not have any
      lights, it is your responsibility to build and wire the light
      tree.</para>

      <para>The application will control the relay board, during the starting
      race countdown the relay board can will have Relay 4 active until 2
      seconds left in the countdown, at 2 seconds it will switch Relay 4 off
      and Relay 3 on, at 1 second it will switch Relay 3 off and Relay 2 on
      and finally at the start of the race it will switch Relay 2 off and
      Relay 1 on. When the race time limit or lap limit is reached race Relay
      1 will turn off and Relay 2 will turn on. When everyone has finished
      their final laps or timed out Relay 2 will turn off and Relay 4 will
      turn on. You can connect lights to these relays to have a start/stop
      light for races.</para>

      <para>Information about the DLP Designs DLP-IOR4 relay board and
      locations to purchase board from can be found here, <link
      xlink:href="http://www.dlpdesign.com/usb/ior4.shtml">www.dlpdesign.com/usb/ior4.shtml</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="Keyboard">
      <title>Keyboard</title>

      <para>If you do not have lap counting hardware to use you can instead
      use the keyboard to register laps for racers. While it is not as
      accurate it can still provide fun racing with a group of friends. Each
      racer must have a unique key assigned when <link
      linkend="CreateNewRacer">Creating the Racer</link>, the key does not
      have to be a number, it can be any key on the keyboard except the
      letters r,s,e and p which are reserved for <link
      linkend="KeyboardShortcuts">Keyboard Shortcuts</link>.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="Theme">
    <title>Theme</title>

    <para>Changing some aspects of the appearance and sounds that the software
    has is possible. To manage a theme you must click the Manage Themes button
    on the General Config Screen. This chapter details some of the options
    that can be changed.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Managing Themes</title>

      <para>Upon clicking the <link linkend="ThemeButton">Manage Themes
      Button</link> on the <link linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config
      Screen</link> a window will pop up with the controls for managing
      themes. The top of this window contains the basic controls to select,
      create, delete, import, export and save themes. Below these controls is
      a tab panel, each tab contains various theme items that can be modified.
      After any changes have been made to a theme you must click the Save
      button for them to be saved. If the save button is not clicked any
      changes will be lost.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Select Theme to Manage:</title>

        <para>This popup menu provides 2 functions. The first is the ability
        to select an existing theme to manage. The second is the ability to
        type in a new name of a theme to create.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Create</title>

        <para>To create a new theme first type in a unique theme name in the
        popup menu then click the Create button. This will create a new theme
        with default theme settings. You can then select the theme to manage
        it.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Delete</title>

        <para>To delete a theme select the theme to manage from the popup menu
        and then click the Delete button. Deletes are permanent, after a theme
        has been deleted there is no way to recover it.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Import</title>

        <para>The import and export functions provide a way to share themes or
        to create backups of your themes. To import a theme just click the
        Import button. A window will pop up asking you to select the theme
        file to import. Selecting a valid file will result in the new theme
        being inserted into the database. If the imported theme has the same
        name as an existing theme you will be prompted to decide what to do.
        You can overwrite the existing theme with the imported theme or if you
        choose not to overwrite the theme the program will add a number to the
        end of the theme name.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Export</title>

        <para>The export function provides a way to save a theme to be shared
        with people or to provide a backup for yourself. To export a theme
        just select the theme from the popup menu and click the Export button.
        A window will pop up allowing you to select where to save the file
        to.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Save</title>

        <para>Any changes to a theme that you wish to keep must be saved. To
        save a change make sure you have a theme selected, make your changes
        and then click the Save button.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Customizing the Theme</title>

      <para>After creating or selecting a theme to manage you can customize
      the various items of a theme using the tab panel on the theme manager
      window. This tab panel has 4 tabs, Images, Buttons, Colors and Sounds.
      Select the appropriate tab for what you want to change on your
      theme.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Images</title>

        <para>This tab panel is used to control the various standard images
        used within the program.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Background</title>

          <para>Clicking the browse button or clicking the existing image
          under the Background heading will allow you to select a new
          background image for the program.</para>

          <para>The default background included is 1920x1200 in size and set
          to not scale. For screens smaller than this resolution the
          application will only display the portion of the background equal to
          the window size. For screens larger than this the remaining window
          space will be filled with the default background color which can be
          selected on the Colors tab.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Scale Background</title>

          <para>By enabling this feature the program will stretch or shrink
          your background image to fit the window. By default this setting is
          off. With the setting off only the portion of the background equal
          to your window size will be displayed.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Main Logo</title>

          <para>To change the Main Logo you need 2 images. One image is the
          logo itself while the other image is a mask. The mask is a black and
          white image that tells the program what part of the logo image
          should be displayed and what part of the logo should be transparent.
          When you click the browse button you will be prompted to select both
          of theses images. First you will be prompted to select the logo
          image, after one has been selected you will be prompted a second
          time to select the mask. The images used for the logo must not
          larger than 522x190. Anything larger than that will be cut off from
          the display.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Countdown Images</title>

          <para>The Countdown Images are displayed on the <link
          linkend="RaceScreen">Race Screen</link> during the initial countdown
          before a race starts. The number after the image name indicates at
          which second of the countdown the image displays. For example
          Countdown 0 is displayed when 0 seconds remain in the countdown
          which is when the race starts, Countdown 1 is displayed when 1
          second remains in the countdown and Countdown 6+ is displayed when 6
          or more seconds remain in the countdown. The image used for
          countdowns must not be greater than 250x108 in size. Anything larger
          than that will be cut off from the display.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Empty Racer</title>

          <para>The Empty Racer image is used on the race screen for slots
          that do not currently have a racer. To change this graphic you need
          two images, the empty racer image and a mask image. The mask image
          tells the program what part of the empty racer image to display and
          what part to make transparent. When you click the browse button you
          will be prompted to select these two images, first the program will
          prompt for the empty racer image and then it will prompt you to
          select the mask image.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Buttons</title>

        <para>On this tab panel you can change the appearance of some of the
        buttons within the program.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Navigation Buttons</title>

          <para>To change Navigation Buttons you must have 3 images. You will
          need the button image, the button image mask file and a mouse over
          image. The button image is the default image displayed and the mouse
          over image is what is displayed when the mouse is over the button.
          The mask file is a black and white file that tells the program what
          parts of the button image are to be displayed and what parts are
          transparent. When you click the Browse button you will be prompted
          to select these three images. The program will first prompt you for
          the button image, then for the mask image and finally for the mouse
          over image.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Documentation Buttons</title>

          <para>The Documentation Buttons are the 4 buttons on the Main Screen
          used to navigate to various parts of the documentation. Two images
          are required for these buttons, the button image and a mask file.
          The mask file tells the program what parts of the button to display
          and what parts are transparent. When you click the Browse button you
          will be prompted to select two images. The program will first prompt
          you for the button image and then for the mask image.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Colors</title>

        <para>The list box on this screen is used to control the various
        colors within the program. To change a color just click the text of
        what you want to change. A color selection window will pop up allowing
        you to customize that particular color.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="SoundEffects">
        <title>Sounds</title>

        <para>While most of the application uses <link linkend="TTS">Text To
        Speech</link> for sound there are 4 sound effects that can be
        customized. The Sounds tab allows you to select new sounds and to play
        the sounds within a theme.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="CustomizeRaceReport">
      <title>Customizing the Race Report</title>

      <para>The logo and club name on the <link
      linkend="GenerateRaceReport">Race Report</link> is controlled by the
      <link linkend="ClubInfo">Club Info</link> settings on the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> Screen.</para>

      <para>The overall appearance of the <link
      linkend="GenerateRaceReport">Race Report</link> is controlled by the
      race.xsl file located in the reports directory. If you are familiar with
      HTML and CSS and you change the colors, appearance and layout of new
      reports by modifying this file. It is a text file so any text editor can
      be used. The race.xsl file only applies to new reports, if it is changed
      existing reports will have to be <link
      linkend="GenerateRaceReport">regenerated</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Customizing the Racer Inventory Report</title>

      <para>The logo and club name on the <link
      linkend="GenerateRacerInventoryReport">Racer Inventory Report</link> is
      controlled by the <link linkend="ClubInfo">Club Info</link> settings on
      the <link linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link>
      Screen.</para>

      <para>The overall appearance of the <link
      linkend="GenerateRacerInventoryReport">Racer Inventor Report</link> is
      controlled by the racerinventory.xsl file located in the reports
      directory. If you are familiar with HTML and CSS and you change the
      colors, appearance and layout of new reports by modifying this file. It
      is a text file so any text editor can be used. The racerinventory.xsl
      file only applies to new reports, if it is changed existing reports will
      have to be <link
      linkend="GenerateRacerInventoryReport">regenerated</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Changing the Logo on the Splash Screen</title>

      <para>When the application first launches there is a splash screen that
      appears with the Flip Side Racing logo before the main window pops up.
      This logo is loaded from the FlipSideRacingLogo.jpg file in the theme
      directory. Overwriting this file with your own logo will cause it to be
      displayed on the splash screen when the application launches. The image
      should be 520x190 or smaller in size. If it is larger than that the
      image will be cut off.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="AdvancedTopics">
    <title>Advanced Topics</title>

    <para>This chapter has sections detailing some of the more advanced things
    that can be done or changed with the program.</para>

    <section xml:id="RaceCarInfoPopUp">
      <title>Adding Options to the Edit Racer Screen</title>

      <para>When creating or editing racers on the <link
      linkend="EditRacersScreen">Edit Racers</link> Screen the pop up menus
      under Race Car Specific Information can be changed. These options are
      controlled by various parts of the program. The different spots used to
      change the options are listed below.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Scale, Chassis, Class and
          Motor:</emphasis> These pop up menus are controlled by the
          raceparts.xml file. You can add or remove options from these menus
          by editing the raceparts.xml file with a text editor. Please make
          sure to keep the file properly formatted and do not remove the
          &lt;&gt;none&lt;&gt; entries for each option.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Make and Model:</emphasis> The make and
          model options are controlled by the database. To add options either
          go to the <link linkend="EditRacersScreen">Edit Racers</link> Screen
          and type text into the Make and Model fields and hit enter or you
          use the <link linkend="EditMakeModel">Edit Make/Model</link> utility
          located on the <link linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General
          Config</link> Screen to add or delete makes and models.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Crystal:</emphasis> The options
          available for the Crystal pop up menu is controlled by the
          crystals.xml file. You can add and remove options for the menu by
          modifying this file with a text editor. The Crystal pop up menu is
          also a combo menu, instead of choosing an option in the menu you can
          type text for whatever crystal you are using. Items entered through
          the menu are not saved to the menu though, you must edit the
          crystals.xml file for it to be a menu option.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="TTS">
      <title>Text to Speech</title>

      <para>The software uses your Operating Systems built in Text To Speech
      capabilities to announce various things during a race such as time
      remaining, ranks, best laps and the count down.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>MAC OS X: On a Mac the Text To Speech settings are located in
          the System Preferences in the System heading under the Speech
          option. Within this preference pane you can change things such as
          the voice used and speed of the speaking rate.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Windows: In Windows to configure Text To Speech settings you
          must go to your control panel and then go to the Speech applet.
          Within this applet you can choose different voices and change the
          speed of the speaking rate.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Linux: For Linux the software is using kttsd for the Text To
          Speech. You must install and configure kttsmgr management utility
          and an appropriate Text To Speech engine for Text To Speech to
          operate in Linux. Festival is a common TTS engine used in Linux and
          will work with kttsmgr.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The default voices in some versions of the various operating
      systems do not sound very good. You can get third party voices that will
      work and sound much better. Here are a few options.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Microsoft Mary and Mike English voices for free can be
          downloaded here, <link
          xlink:href="http://www.imptec.com/SpeechXP.exe">www.imptec.com/SpeechXP.exe</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A list of various third party voices that you must purchase
          can be found here, <link
          xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/speech/evaluation/thirdparty/engines.mspx">www.microsoft.com/speech/evaluation/thirdparty/engines.mspx</link>.
          Some of these companies such as AT&amp;T and Cepstral have voices
          that will also work in Mac and Linux.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Free French and German voices for Windows can be downloaded
          from here, <link
          xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/reader/developers/downloads/tts.aspx">www.microsoft.com/reader/developers/downloads/tts.aspx</link>.
          You must install the Microsoft Reader from here, <link
          xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/reader/downloads/pc.aspx">www.microsoft.com/reader/downloads/pc.aspx</link>
          before installing the French and German voices.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Various clubs have been happy with the sound of the third party
      AT&amp;T voices.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="Translations">
      <title>Translations</title>

      <para>It is possible to translate the speech in the program to another
      language. By default the americanenglish.xml file located in the
      translations directory is used. The file is well documented and can be
      edited with a text editor to create a new translation. After editing the
      file save it with a new name reflecting the language that the text was
      translated to. After creating a new translation you will have to select
      the translation through the <link linkend="SpeechFile">Speech
      File</link> option on the <link linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General
      Config</link> Screen. If you are translating the speech to a different
      language you will need to change your <link xlink:href="TTS">Text To
      Speech</link> settings to a language other than English.</para>

      <para>Two translations are already included with the software, German
      and French. They are also located in the translations directory.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Change Racer Text Color</title>

      <para>To change the racer text color used on the <link
      linkend="RaceScreen">Race</link> or <link
      linkend="StatisticsScreen">Statistics</link> Screens refer to the <link
      linkend="ChangeTextColor">Change Text Color</link> section of the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> chapter.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Graph Line Colors</title>

      <para>To change the racer graph line colors used on the <link
      linkend="StatisticsScreen">Statistics</link> Screen refer to the <link
      linkend="ChangeTextColor">Change Text Color</link> section of the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> chapter.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Increase the Total Number of Racers Per Race</title>

      <para>The total number of racers allowed per race is configurable. Refer
      to the <link linkend="GUISettings">GUI Settings</link> section located
      on the <link linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> Screen
      to modify this limit.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Upgrading the Software</title>

      <para>This software is under active development, it is recommended to
      download the latest copy of the software from <link
      xlink:href="http://www.flipsideracing.org">www.flipsideracing.org</link>.
      While there is no automated process for upgrading to the latest version
      of the software upgrading is fairly simple. After downloading the latest
      version of the software you can copy the FlipSideDB and preferences.xml
      file from your old copy of the software to the new. Unless you have
      manually edited other files such as the xml files used by the software
      those two files are all that are needed from the previous
      version.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Rename a Race</title>

      <para>Currently the software does not provide a way to rename a race
      after it has been ran. But since the race data is stored in an SQLite
      <link linkend="Database">database</link> you can use a SQLite database
      management tool to modify any information in the <link
      linkend="Database">database</link> directly. If you do modify the
      database directly it is recommended that you make a backup copy
      first.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="Database">
      <title>Database Information</title>

      <para>All of the racer and race information is stored in an SQLite
      database. This database is located in the program directory and named
      FlipSideDB. This file must exist for the software to operate.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using a Secondary Lap Counter</title>

      <para>Two lap counters can be used at once with this software. This
      allows you the flexibility to do rally or drag style timing or use 2 lap
      counters to cover a wider track. To configure a secondary lap counter
      refer to the <link linkend="SecondaryCOMDevice">Secondary COM Device
      Selection</link> section of the <link
      linkend="GeneralConfigScreen">General Config</link> Screen.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="KeyboardShortcuts">
      <title>Keyboard Shortcuts</title>

      <para>There are a few keyboard shortcuts available to perform actions
      within the software.</para>

      <para>If you want the software to announce the current ranks of all the
      racers hit the "r" key on the keyboard. You can also start a race by
      hitting "s", end a race by hitting "e", or pause a race by hitting
      "p".</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="KyoshoGenericTags">
      <title>Using Generic RFID Tags with the Kyosho IC Lap Counter</title>

      <para>Generic <link linkend="RFID">RFID</link> tags must be initialized
      before they can work with the Kyosho IC lap counter. A separate program
      called Kyosho RFID Tag Init has been created to initialize generic tags
      and can be downloaded from the <link
      xlink:href="http://www.flipsideracing.org">www.flipsideracing.org</link>
      website.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">WARNING: Do not initialize Kyosho tags such
      as those on the dNaNo, if you do they will probably no longer work with
      the Kyosho software. Only generic RFID tags need
      initialized.</emphasis></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Troubleshooting Errors</title>

      <para>In the event that you are encountering a bug please contact us for
      support. If the problem is resulting in an error message or crash the
      program will attempt to send the information about the error
      automatically. If it can not send the information it will create a file
      called dump.txt that contains details about the error. Please send us
      this information along with any details you can provide about what
      occurred to help us with troubleshooting the problem.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="Support">
    <title>Support</title>

    <para>If you need additional help with this software you can either
    contact us directly by using the Contact Link on the main website at <link
    xlink:href="http://www.flipsideracing.org">www.flipsideracing.org</link>
    or visit the forum hosted by <link
    xlink:href="http://mini-zracer.com/forums/forumdisplay.php?f=150">www.mini-zracer.com</link>.
    You will need to register in order to access the support forum.</para>

    <para>We welcome any constructive feedback.</para>
  </chapter>
</book>
